{"tossups": [{"question": "This novel\u2019s reputation increased when it was assigned as required reading by David Riesman in a sociology class shortly after its publication. Shortly after this novel was picked up by a Book of the Month club, its author moved from his New York City apartment to his longtime home in Cornish, New Hampshire. Mark David Chapman bought a copy of this book the day that he killed John Lennon. For ten points, name this novel about the rebellious teen Holden Caulfield by J.D. Salinger.", "answer": "The<b> Catcher in the Rye</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "Parson Brownlow was a vocal opponent of joining this group, using his<em> Knoxville Whig</em> newspaper to oppose it. Cotton imports from India and Egypt allowed the United Kingdom to refuse to recognize this group, which employed A. P. Hill and George Pickett in its armed forces. Alexander Hamilton Stephens served as vice-president of, for ten points, what unrecognized nation whose only president, Jefferson Davis, resided in Richmond, Virginia?", "answer": "<b> Confederate</b> States of America (accept word forms, like the<b> Confederacy</b>; accept the<b> CSA</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Philip the Good ordered the construction of one of these objects called Mons Meg. An early metal version of these objects was called the<em> pot-de-fer</em>, and culverins were portable types of these items. The Hungarian engineer Orban designed a massive one of these objects that malfunctioned and killed him. Vauban designed star forts to defend against these weapons, which Mehmed II used to destroy the walls of Constantinople in 1453. For ten points, name these gunpowder-based artillery pieces.", "answer": "<b> cannon</b>s (or<b> bombard</b>s; prompt on artillery before mentioned; prompt on supergun; do not prompt on gun, weapon, or other too-vague terms)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 2004 in this country, TV host Rania al-Baz was severely beaten by her husband for answering the phone without permission. This country\u2019s prominent businesswomen include Lubna Olayan, who gave a historic address in 2004 at the Jeddah Economic Forum, held on this country\u2019s west coast. For ten points, name this country where, in 2017, King Salman lifted a restriction on driver\u2019s licenses that will, eventually, allow women to drive in Riyadh and Mecca.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Saudi Arabia</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This organization was investigated by the Kefauver Committee, which failed to prove its existence. Six years later, dozens of members of this organization fled into the forest around Joseph Barbara\u2019s house in Apalachin, New York, after a meeting called there by Vito Genovese was raided by police. The \u201cFive Families,\u201d including the Gambino family, were central to, for ten points, what Italian-American organized crime outfit?", "answer": "the American<b> mafia</b> (accept La<b> Cosa Nostra</b> or<b> LCN</b>; prompt on the mob) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Two answers required. A conflict between these two countries was sparked by the destruction of a bakery owned by a man named Remontel. Maximilian I was installed by one of these countries on the throne of the other. Ignacio Zaragoza led one of these two countries in victory against the other at the Battle of Puebla, which is commemorated by Cinco de Mayo. For ten points, name these two countries that clashed under leaders like Porfirio Diaz and Napoleon III.", "answer": "<b> Mexico and France</b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Frank Crowe served as the chief engineer of this project, for which Six Companies, Inc. was formed. J.G. Tierney and his son, Patrick Tierney, were the first and last people to die in this project\u2019s construction. Boulder City was built near this structure, which slowly changed its name from Boulder Dam in the 1940s. For ten points, name this arch-gravity dam built over the Colorado River during the Great Depression, named for a US President.", "answer": "<b> Hoover Dam</b> (accept<b> Boulder Dam</b> before \u201cBoulder\u201d is first read)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "With Edmund Eyre, this man led the British forces that raided the town of New London and captured Fort Griswold at the Battle of Groton Heights. This man married Peggy Shippen while in charge of the military garrison in Philadelphia. The capture of John Andre exposed this man\u2019s plans to weaken the American defenses along the Hudson River in New York. For ten points, name this American commander who defected to the British, thus becoming a legendary traitor.", "answer": "Benedict<b> Arnold</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "After this event, mayor Eugene Schmitz ordered troops under Adolphus Greely and Frederick Funston to \u201cshoot to kill\u201d any looters. This event prompted renovations of Telegraph Hill and Fisherman\u2019s Wharf, and its destruction of record houses in Chinatown allowed many immigrants to claim American residency. Thousands of people died in, for ten points, what 1906 natural disaster in Northern California\u2019s Bay Area?", "answer": "1906<b> San Francisco earthquake</b> (and/or 1906<b> San Francisco fire</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One of these systems was invented in the 15th century by Sejong the Great of the Joseon Dynasty; its 40 elements can be combined into over 11 thousand blocks. The oldest of these systems is an abjad with 22 entries; that Phoenician system inspired modern examples such as Greek, Cyrillic, and Latin. The first two entries in the Hebrew system inspires the name of, for ten points, what term for a set of letters used to write a language?", "answer": "<b> alphabet</b> (prompt on writing system; do not accept syllabary)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "A painting of this conflict shows Francis Barlow addressing a long-haired officer and other captured men; that work,<em> Prisoners From the Front</em>, was made by Winslow Homer, who created sketches of camp life in this war for the magazine<em> Harper\u2019s Weekly</em>. Alexander Gardner and Mathew Brady were prominent photographers of, for ten points, what war, depicted in Brady\u2019s photograph<em> The Dead of Antietam</em>?", "answer": "American<b> Civil War</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this country, indigenous soldiers who fought for Portuguese interests were known as Lascarins. During the sack of Vijayabahu, three members of a royal family in this country</b> <b>killed the King of Kotte. A temple containing a (+)</b> <b>tooth relic of Siddhartha Gautama</b> <b>can be found in this country\u2019s city of Kandy; that temple was bombed in the 1990s by a terrorist group known as LTTE. (*)</b> Tamil and Sinhalese are the major languages of, for ten points, what country, once known as Ceylon, found on an island south of India?", "answer": "<b> Sri Lanka</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Cantilevers are used in the \u201catomic force\u201d type of these devices, which were inspired by a scanning, tunnelling type that won the 1986 Physics Nobel. Ernst Ruska and Max Knoll worked to develop types of these devices based on raster scattering of (+) electrons. In the 17th century, Anton Van Leeuwenhoek built one of these devices to observe what he called animalcules, organisms that Robert (*) </b> Hooke later noted were made up of cells. For ten points, name these scientific tools that allow you to see very small things.", "answer": "<b> microscope</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Emperor Gallienus slaughtered a force of these people at Naissus in 269 AD. A century later, a group of these people led by Fritigern slaughtered the Romans and killed Emperor</b> <b>Valens in the Battle of (+)</b> <b>Adrianople. This ethnic group\u2019s 3rd century AD appearance</b> <b>in the frontiers of Europe hastened the fall of Rome. (*)</b> Alaric and Theoderic were among the leaders of, for ten points, what Germanic ethnic group that was split into western and eastern branches prefixed by \u201cVisi-\u201d and \u201cOstro-?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Goth</b>s (accept<b> Visigoths</b> and/or<b> Ostrogoths</b> at any point; prompt on barbarians)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Help for this event\u2019s victims was swift, thanks to policies established after the \u201clivebait\u201dsquadron\u2019s destruction. William Turner\u2019s failure to zigzag may have led to this event, which</b> <b>took place off the (+)</b> <b>took place off the (+)</b> <b>Old Head of Kinsale and involved a disputed number of torpedoes.</b> <b>An Imperial (*)</b> German Embassy warning appeared in ads prior to, for ten points, what 1915 event German Embassy warning appeared in ads prior to, for ten points, what 1915 event in which a Cunard liner was sunk by a German U-boat, killing over 100 Americans and pushing the US into World War I?", "answer": "<b> sinking</b> of the RMS<b> Lusitania</b>  (1) <b>In case of one war, this country planned to rush through its northern neighbor</b> <b>to the Dyle River. This country\u2019s navy was attacked by its own ally at Mers-el-K\u00b4ebir</b> <b>and forced to scuttle its own ships at (+)</b> <b>Toulon. This country built a defensive</b> <b>Toulon. This country built a defensive</b> <b>structure called the Maginot Line that was bypassed by a (*)</b> <b>structure called the Maginot Line that was bypassed by a (*)</b> blitzkrieg through the Ardennes forest. For ten points, name this country that was split into German-occupied north and Vichy south after its defeat in World War II. ANSWER:<b> France</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}